Finding Aid for Epiphany Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.) Records 1895-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Epiphany Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.) Records 1895-1975, 1930-1973
Epiphany Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
4 oversize volumes
1 linear feet
Episcopal parish established in 1894 in Detroit, Michigan and merged with Church of the Messiah (Detroit, Mich.) in 1973. Records include minutes, registers and a small amount of administrative material.
98115 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred through Rev. Stephen Bartlett, Rector, in June 1998. Donor no. 8735
The collection is open for research.
"In the summer and fall of 1894, the subject of establishing an Episcopal Mission at some point in the thickly settled and rapidly growing section of the city near the water works was being considered." The first meeting to establish a mission in this Detroit, Michigan neighborhood was held late in that year at the Park Avenue home of George E. Thompson. Sometime in January of 1895, representatives of twenty-four families signed an application to formerly organize a parish. Originally known as Water Works Mission, the name was soon changed to Epiphany Mission, and in the fall of 1895 the "old Rose school house (20 x 80 ft.) ... was purchased for $50 and moved across open fields to a location on Cadillac."
Early in 1899, the Reverend Overton Tarraut was appointed the first missionary in charge of Epiphany. It was during his incumbency that the church moved to what would become a permanent Detroit location at Cadillac and Kercheval.
From 1909 to 1919, population in the area grew quickly and increasing numbers of people took part in activities at the neighborhood church. Soon the need was felt for a new church and parish hall, plans and specifications were prepared, and a lot on the north side of the existing property was purchased for $6,000. By 1924, however, building plans were set aside, and a community center was favored instead. Support for this notion was impressively strong - one hundred-sixty volunteers raised $93,000 in a seven day campaign. Community House of Epiphany Episcopal Church was dedicated on January 22, 1926.
In the late forties and into the sixties, Epiphany experienced negative effects of social change and urban decay, suffering a gradual decline in membership. When H. Irving Mayson was appointed archdeacon in 1970, he proposed a creative solution to pressing problems. The Diocese supported the financing of a black and white team ministry for Epiphany and an adjacent parish, Church of the Messiah.
Early in this ministry, an editor of the Epiphany / Messiah newsletter wrote: "This life-long member of the Church of the Epiphany has been concerned about the future of the parish for a number of years. We have been without a rector. Our black and white communicants are troubled by vandalism of the buildings and thefts from persons and property. Many neighborhood youth are resentful of what they mistakenly call a 'white church' in a black inner-city area. Our tiny, yet faithful congregation is frustrated because we lack funds to finance the salary of a staff whereby we can open up full-time a fine community building for neighborhood use. This would be our symbol of sincerity and a means to best relate to community needs. We still require this funding ... It has been a painful experience to see our feeble efforts at existence lead us toward slow death. I believe the church belongs to the neighborhood and that service along with worship is the way to spread the Good News of the Gospel."
Although faith was temporarily sustained through ties with Messiah, Epiphany never regained its once strong place in the neighborhood. The two churches eventually merged, and the last service was held at Epiphany on November 11, 1973. In 1975 the vestry passed a resolution recommending that Epiphany buildings be sold.
The records of Epiphany Episcopal Church are comprised of three series: Minutes, 1895-1949; Registers, 1896-1969; Administrative, 1911-1976.
The records of Epiphany Church mainly document the history and membership of the church prior to its merging with Church of the Messiah in 1974. It also provides evidence, although scant, of efforts to remain viable and of the disposition of property and memorials when the church was put up for sale. Researchers should note that the Bentley Historical Library also holds the records of the Church of the Messiah (2.5 linear ft., 1875-1988).
Subjects:
Epiphany Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.
- Minutes
  The Minutes series is the most substantial documentation of Epiphany's evolution, offering a complete run of written records beginning in 1895, one year after steps were taken towards organizing the mission. Researchers can trace activities through the late 40s, but unfortunately, it is there that the records become sparse. There is little documentation in the series of the effect of neighborhood changes on Epiphany Episcopal in the 50s and 60s, or of the collaboration and eventual merging with Church of the Messiah.
  - 1895-April 1903 (Box 1)
  - June 1903-December 1914 (Volume 1)
  - January 1915-December 1930 (Box 1)
  - January 1931-January 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1973 (Box 1)
- Registers
  The Registers include membership data from 1896 through 1969. The most complete records cover the years 1930 through 1969, including citations on marriages, baptisms, burials, and communicants. There are also registers for church services held from 1930 through 1973.
  - Membership
    - 1896-1915 (Box 1)
      (Includes church history)
    - 1915-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1969
      - Rectors, Communicants, Baptisms, Burials (Box 1)
      - Marriage Register (Volume 2)
      - Index (Volume 3)
  - Services
    - March 1930-October 1940 (Box 1)
    - January 1940-December 1959 (Box 1)
    - January 1960-November 1963 (Box 1)
    - September 1968-1973 (Box 1)
- Administrative
  A small administrative series is the only source of information beyond the bound formal records in the other two series. Comprised mainly of financial records, along with a small amount of correspondence, the series is most effective in documenting the final disposition of furnishings, memorials, and church property.
  - Correspondence 1911-1976, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial
    - Register 1959-1973 (Volume 4)
    - Correspondence and reports 1930-1938 (Box 1)
    - Reports 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    (includes mimeographed minutes and a few newsletters)